Good
morning. Today is the November 8th, it’s the 20th of מרחשון, Marheshvan,
and yesterday we got to just around the bottom of ג עמוד
ב. Gimel Amud Bet. We
are in the second wide line. So this whole discussion of שמיטה
Shemita had been brought up as a tangent because our משנה Mishnah
had discussed the possibility of a loan that had been lent out
for a ten-year term, and we said, wait a second, wouldn’t שמיטה
Shemita always be intervening and therefore they would always be, the loan
would end up being forgiven? So that was option number one. And
then we had a discussion of the how שמיטת כספים Shemita Kesafim
works based on an opinion of אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar
Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel. So now we have three more statements from
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda quoting, quoting רב Rav and quoting שמואל. Shmuel.
So the first one will be from the bottom here and this
is אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav. So
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda quotes his teacher רב: Rav: הפותח בית הצואר
בשבת, Hapote'ach beit hatzavar beshabbat, someone opens up the neck of a
new shirt on שבת, Shabbat, חייב חטאת. hayyav hatat. So that’s a
biblical violation of שבת. Shabbat. We can go into some of the
discussion of that maybe, but basically the sense is that either it’s
completing the act of the, it’s a constructive kind of tearing. You’re
tearing open the seam in some way and therefore ripping those stitches
is a productive act which creates the opening in the garment so
that you can wear it. Presumably the way they used to weave
the clothes back then, they used to baste together the seam and
then when you would buy it you would rip it open. So
that’s the way it was made. So the ripping open of the
neck is destructive but it’s constructive. It’s destructive to the stitching but
it’s constructive to the garment as a whole and that’s why it’s
not מקלקל. mekalkel. Usually we say כל המקלקלין פטורין. kol hamekalkelin peturin.
Destructive actions on שבת Shabbat are generally not, you wouldn’t be liable
for. But in this case it’s a destructive act with a constructive
consequence, so we say that it actually is considered constructive. So מתקיף
לה רב כהנא. matkif lah Rav Kahana. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana
asked רב יהודה: Rav Yehuda: Wait a second, I don’t understand, how
can you say you’re חייב חטאת? hayyav hatat? וכי מה בין זה
למגופת חבית? vekhi mah bein zeh lemegufat havit? How is that different
than the lid of a barrel?
That’s more practical these days, a bottle... exactly.
So the whole
question... exactly. So well but not everything is permitted for food on
שבת. Shabbat. There are all sorts of reasons why we would be
more prohibitive, but because there’s a whole question of bottle caps and
many different פוסקים poskim have ruled many different ways based on how
they evaluate the reality of the question of what is opening the
lid of a bottle cap and was the lid a really its
own כלי kli beforehand or not, did it serve a function, was
it meant to be opened and closed and all these other kinds
of questions.
It was meant to be opened and closed, I mean...
well but it was meant to be opened but not meant to
be re-closed, different kinds of things, what’s the function of the cap.
And also is it like, as you mentioned, I guess it’s a
constructive with the bottle so to speak or is it put on
separately?
One second, I actually have to run to the bathroom for like
one sec, I’ll be right back.
He
still does that with men's jackets, sometimes they sew the pocket.
Oh yeah, the pocket.
Right, and then you have to take that off.
Yeah, yeah that's what... it's annoying because sometimes I just don't remember.
Oh I know, and then it's שבת, Shabbos, you mean?
Yeah and then you're like ah! But then too late and then
afterwards...
and that's my שבת Shabbos clothes.
And then you can't wear it again until next, another שבת, Shabbos,
and then you have the same problem again and again.
Sort of like tightening the knot on a ציצית tzitzit which you
can't do on שבת Shabbat either.
You can't. Uh-huh. What about what's this about the bottle caps? Here's
the question about whether you can take a bottle cap off.
Right, some people don't, some people mean like let's say like you
know you buy a bottle of
soda right and it's unopened you know and then you have that
little you know the plastic top and you open...
yeah that's the part you mean. Yeah, but sometimes I've heard that
was a question of if you made a ring, if there was
a ring underneath. You know like the grape juice? Grape juice
bottles? They have a... when you open the plastic there's a little
ring that...
but that's what
we were talking about.
Oh no,
not the thing around what holds in the... not the whole thing
around the neck and the bottle cap. Sometimes there's that. We're talking
about the bottle cap itself.
Itself. Okay. So but you
know the issue is... sorry about that.
Did you already
talk
about that?
What about the cap?
Yeah, because it's a very big topic. I mean the sense is
basically if you think that the cap existed as its own functional
כלי kli beforehand to keep the... lid closed then separate from the
bottle then actually you haven't done anything new by unscrewing it. But
if you think that the cap is in some way connected or
or a single unit with the bottle then you're breaking it open
and making a new functional piece which is going to be the
cap.
But it's always formed separately, it's not like it's part.
Right, so but and פוסקים poskim have gone to great lengths discussing
it, the חזון איש Chazon Ish and the originated really especially with
the discussion of cans before it even was a question of bottles.
Opening the lid of a can on שבת Shabbat and the question
of
are you going to use the the can again afterwards.
Okay. Okay.
Okay we're going to let him cry. Okay so.
Okay so חבצו פי תתא דצוארא בשבת חייב חטאת. chavtzo pi tatta
de-tzavara be-Shabbat chayav chatat.
So רב כהנה Rav Kahana asks וכי מה בין זה למגופת חבית.
ve-chi mah bein zeh le-megupat chavit. How is that different than the
lid of the barrel? So אמר ליה amar lei זה חיבור וזה
אינו חיבור. zeh chibur ve-zeh einu chibur. That is the the the
neck of the container, the neck of the shirt is actually closed.
Exactly. And and the lid of the barrel is not actually attached
to the barrel. It's some kind of a separate separate piece. ואמר
רב יהודה אמר רב ve-amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav a new a
new discussion. So the point is that רב כהנה Rav Kahana asked
this question and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda had an answer to his
question that he felt was a satisfactory answer, that רב כהנה's Rav
Kahana challenge goes answered since we've said oh so ripping open the
shirt would would really be a problem on שבת Shabbat but not
opening up the barrel. Okay. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב שלשה לוגין
מים שנפלו לתוכן קורטוב של יין. ve-amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav shelosha
lugin mayim she-naflu le-tochan kortov shel yayin. If I had three לוג
log of water
into
which fell a very small amount, one קורטוב kortov of wine. What
happens if red wine falls into water?
The water turns red a little bit but it's diluted.
The problem is and we said ומראיהן כמראה יין. u-mareihen ke-mareh yayin.
There's enough pigment from the wine that the water has been colored
red from the wine falling into them. ונפלו למקווה. ve-naflu le-mikveh. And
then these three plus לוג log of now red water fell into
a מקווה. mikveh. לא פסלוהו. lo pesaluhu. It does not disqualify the
מקווה. mikveh. Okay now מתקיף לה רב כהנה. matkif lah Rav Kahana.
רב כהנה Rav Kahana challenges רב יהודה Rav Yehuda again and he
says וכי מה בין זה למי צבע. ve-chi mah bein zeh le-mei
tzeva. How is that different than water that's dying water? So what
would happen, people the way you dye a fabric or dye clothing
is you dissolve the dyes in water. You take the wool or
the linen or whatever and you soak it in or you cook
it in in the dye water and then the dye water still
has pigment in it or whatever. So if dye water fell into
a מקווה mikveh then it does פסול pasul the מקווה. mikveh. So
what's the difference? Why is is red water that was made red
from wine different from water that was turned a color from the
dye? Okay דתנן רבי יוסי אומר מי צבע פוסלין את המקווה בשלשה
לוגין. di-tenan Rabbi Yossi omer mei tzeva poslin et ha-mikveh be-shelosha lugin.
And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says that dying water can disqualify מקווה
mikveh in a measurement of three לוג. log. אמר ליה רבא. amar
lei Rava.
Now רבא Rava comes to defend רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, so somewhat
later actually. התם מיא דצבע מקרו. hatam maya de-tziva mikru. That's where
they're called dying water. הכא חמרא מזיגא מקרי. hacha chamra maziga mikrei.
But in a case where a small amount of wine fell into
water, the amount perhaps we could say the amount of pigment but
also the character of the liquid, the character of the solution is
not dying water but the character is that it's diluted wine. יין
מזוג. yayin mazug. Diluted wine is just wine. When they would drink
the wine in תלמודיק Talmudic times very often they would dilute it
even as much as only one quarter wine and three quarters water,
things like that or one sixth wine, five sixths water. So it
would be very dilute but at the same time it would have
enough pigment to look like wine and they would call it wine.
So the sense is that wine does not disqualify a מקווה mikveh
because the amount of coloration and also the character of the liquid
is different. It's not water, it's just a different liquid. So it's
actually less problematic in the מקווה. mikveh. Okay. Okay
so that's why that if the קורטוב kortov of wine falls into
three לוג log of water and then the water falls into the
מקווה, mikveh, it's no longer water falling into a מקווה mikveh which
we would go by the color, as as we just say oh
it's wine that fell into a מקווה mikveh and we actually don't
care as much. It's an interesting loophole in this case that a
small amount of wine transforms the water into יין מזוג yayin mazug
diluted wine and that makes it less less stringent in the הלכה.
halacha. Okay.
והא תני רבי חייא ve-ha tani Rabbi Chiya orange juice, orange juice.
I don't remember off top of my head מי פירות. mei peirot.
I think מי פירות mei peirot fall in the same category as
the wine for this, that it's not water. So it's some other
liquid. Therefore it's actually it's a lesser stringency. Right? Orange juice or
something like that. But again we have here the whole question will
be about things that have a color. Some of the positions of
the תנאים Tannaim at least are it always goes by the. appearance.
There are two different ways we could assess the מקוה. mikvah. Things
would have to do with water, we wouldn't go by appearance, we
would go by the amount of יין yayin or מים שאובים mayim
sheuvim or something like that. Disqualified water that goes into a מקוה
mikvah we go by volume, but if it's something that's a different
liquid like wine or milk or something like that, we go by
how it changes the color. So that's sort of the difference here.
Okay. והתניא, veha tanya, don't we have this ברייתא, braita, this משנה
mishna from מקוואות? mikvaot? רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, הורידו את המקוה, horeidu
et hamikvah, that is, it reduces the מקוה, mikvah, that is what
that basically we can't count that amount of liquid towards the מקוה
mikvah because it's not good מקוה mikvah water. So אמר רבא לא
קשיא הא רבי יוחנן בן נורי הא רבנן. amar Rava lo kashya
ha Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri ha Rabbanan. It's actually מחלוקת machloket between
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri and the other רבנן,
Rabbanan, דתנן שלשה לוגין מים חסר קורטוב שנפלו לתוכן קורטוב יין. detnan
sheloshah lugin mayim chaser kartov she-naflu le-tochan kartov yayin. So we had
three לוג log less one קורטוב, kartov, so slightly less than three
לוג log of water into which fell a קורטוב kartov of
יין, yayin, ומראיהן כמראה יין ונפלו למקוה לא פסלוהו. u-mareihen kemarei yayin
ve-naflu lamikvah lo pasalu-hu. It doesn't פסל pasal the מקוה mikvah because
it's not three לוג log of water. וכן שלשה לוגין מים חסר
קורטוב שנפלו לתוכן קורטוב חלב, ve-khen sheloshah lugin mayim chaser kartov she-naflu
le-tochan kartov chalav, or three לוג log of water that fell into
it a קורטוב kartov of milk,
ומראיהן כמראה מים ונפלו למקוה לא פסלוהו. u-mareihen kemarei mayim ve-naflu lamikvah
lo pasalu-hu.
And then it falls into the מקוה, mikvah, it doesn't פסל pasal
the מקוה. mikvah. רבי יוחנן
בן נורי אומר הכל הולך אחר המראה. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer
hakol holekh achar hamarei. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
says that it all goes according to the appearances, so we don't
actually care about the volume. Sure, thank you.
It all goes according to the appearances and not according to the
volume. So הא מיבעיא בעי ליה לרב פפא, ha mibaya ba'ei leh
le-Rav Pappa, so now this will be the question that רב פפא
Rav Pappa asked. איבעיא ליה לרב פפא רב תני חסר קורטוב ברישא.
iba'aya leh le-Rav Pappa Rav tani chaser kartov be-reisha. רב, Rav, when
רב Rav taught this משנה, mishna, he said the case of חסר
קורטוב, chaser kartov, that it was three לוג log minus a קורטוב
kartov in the רישא reisha case, the first case in the משנה
mishna that was with the יין. yayin. אבל שלשה לוגין לתנא קמא
פסולי, aval sheloshah lugin le-Tana Kama pasulei, but he thinks that the
תנא קמא Tana Kama holds that three לוג log actually will be
פסול, pasul, will disqualify the מקוה. mikvah. ואתא רבי יוחנן למימר, ve-ata
Rabbi Yochanan lemeimar, and when רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri comes to disagree, what does he say? הכל הולך אחר המראה.
hakol holekh achar hamarei. He comes to say that everything just follows
the appearance. ורב אמר כרבי יוחנן בן נורי, ve-Rav omer ke-Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri, and רב Rav says the הלכה halacha follows רבי יוחנן
בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. או דילמא, odilma, or that's possibility
number one, a different way to read the משנה. mishna. ודילמא רב
לא תני חסר קורטוב ברישא. u-dilma Rav lo tani chaser kartov be-reisha.
רב's Rav first case in the משנה mishna with the יין yayin
does not say חסר קורטוב, chaser kartov, that it was missing a
קורטוב, kartov, it was just three full לוג log at the beginning.
רבי יוחנן בן נורי כי פליג אסיפא הוא דפליג, Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri ki palig a-seifa hu de-palig, and רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri is disagreeing with the second case in the משנה.
mishna. ורב דאמר כדברי הכל. ve-Rav de-amar ke-divrei hakol.
Wait, where, where is רב Rav in this?
Sorry, that רב's Rav statement going all the way back to the
beginning, where was רב? Rav? רב's Rav statement was on the bottom
of ג עמוד ב gimmel amud bet
because רב Rav is the one who said when שלשה לוגין מים
שנפלו לתוכן קורטוב של יין מראיהן כמראה יין. sheloshah lugin mayim she-naflu
le-tochan kartov shel yayin mareihen kemarei yayin. So if there were three
לוג log of water, and we're debating, is it חסר קורטוב chaser
kartov or not, that is, is it three full לוג log or
is it two point seven,
and then a little bit of יין yayin fell in, and then
the whole thing fell into the מקוה. mikvah. So the ratios will
be slightly different, that is, is it three לוג log of water,
or is it less than three לוג log of water is really
the question.
And רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri is רבי יוחנן
בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri disagreeing with both clauses of the
משנה mishna or just the second one? Okay.
רב
לא תני חסר קורטוב ברישא רבי יוחנן כי פליג אסיפא הוא דפליג
ורב דאמר כדברי הכל. Rav lo tani chaser kartov be-reisha Rabbi Yochanan
ki palig a-seifa hu de-palig ve-Rav de-amar ke-divrei hakol. And רב's Rav
statement would fit according to both רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and the
רבנן Rabbanan in our משנה. mishna. Okay. לרב פפא איבעיא ליה, le-Rav
Pappa iba'aya leh, so for רב פפא, Rav Pappa, this was a
question. לרבא פשיטא ליה, le-Rava peshita leh, and for רבא, Rava, רבא
Rava thought that the answer was obvious because we saw what רבא
Rava had said, רבא's Rava answer was that this was רבי יוחנן
בן נורי's Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri position and this was the רבנן's
Rabbanan position. That is, that רב's Rav position only accords with רבי
יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri but not both. Okay.
אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef,
I'm sorry, I have to go to the bathroom again.
So what food? I thought you could open all foods on שבת
shabbat if you wanted to eat.
Not so simple, and then there's this מחלוקת machloket also, like
let's
say you have something...
Like a bag of potato chips, right?
Oh right, that I understand.
Okay. You gotta open that, right? So, you know, some people may
not even want to do that. And let's say, yeah, let's say
something with resealable, like let's say like a bag of almonds, right?
With a resealable like the thing on top?
Yeah. Is that all right?
But you know what I mean is like you're going to make
it, like open it like a big thing, right? You know it's
resealable.
Right. But I mean because first you tear off the upper seal
and then you could open and close that seal.
Right. So, you know, can you do that? Because, you know, now
you're starting to
make something functional
and it'll be reused that part or and it'll be reused, right?
So, you know, some some would say no. You know, same idea
of like let's say opening a box of cereal. Like not like
a one serving kind of thing.
You know, a big, you
get like a big thing.
Yeah, yeah, right.
You get like a big thing.
You can't open a box of cereal...
but you know
but
the other...
so you know some...
because you're not eating it all on שבת? Shabbos? Yeah.
If it's not all to be used right away.
Right.
Oh, okay, interesting.
You're creating a... Right.
...a thing. Right.
I before it was whatever...
Right, but others would say that, you know, look at the end
of the day, it's not like you're going to keep this, at
some point it's going to be done. You know what I mean?
Right, like once you're done with all the almonds you're going to
throw out the, you know, the bag that it comes in, you're
not going to use it for anything else. Once you're done with
the... once you're done with the cereal box...
Almost everything you tear on שבת Shabbos you're going to have leftovers
probably, you're going to eat after...
No, no, no, but the issue is opening is making the כלי.
klee. You know? Oh, okay. It's considered making the כלי klee
because it will be used is more than one time use. Oh.
But at the end of the day you're going to throw it
out.
The כלי. klee. Yeah.
Right, you're going to throw out the cereal box, you're
going to throw out the... not a permanent...
Right, it's not permanent.
The thing is that you start with a box that's totally sealed.
Right.
And then you turn it into something that is openable. Right. You've
now turned it into a usable
כלי klee that can hold things.
And was totally closed up. It doesn't...
see people people go both ways on this. Yeah.
I think people generally try to open in advance and then there
are people who say if you open on שבת Shabbos you have
to just throw it in... Okay,
sorry about that.
Okay, those are
the potato chips and then he opens the top in...
Okay,
sorry about that. I'm not feeling 100% this morning, sorry. Okay. אמר
רב
יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. So what does רב יוסף Rav Yosef say?
לא שמיע לי הא שמעתא. Lo Shamia Li Ha Shmaita.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef says I never heard this whole discussion, that
is what רב Rav's way of teaching this משנה Mishna and רב
Rav's response and how how to interpret the משנה Mishna or how
to parse the משנה, Mishna, which phrase, whether to include חסר קרטוב
Chaser Karto or not. רב יוסף Rav Yosef says I never heard
this teaching. אמר ליה אביי את אמרת לן ניהלן והכי אמרת לן
ניהלן. Amar Lei Abaye ad amart la nihan vehachi amart nihan. אביי
Abaye says to רב יוסף Rav Yosef who was his teacher, actually
no, you taught it to us and this is how you taught
it to us. It's interesting that אביי Abaye has a different memory
of that experience than רב יוסף Rav Yosef in later in life,
perhaps. Okay, or אביי Abaye had a very good memory. דרב לא
תני חסר קרטוב
ברישא. De Rav Lo Tanei Chaser Karto Beresha. רב Rav's statement about
the first half of the משנה Mishna about the wine does not
include the phrase חסר קרטוב, Chaser Karto, so as we're talking about
a full three לוג log of water with a קרטוב kartov of
wine falling in. Okay. רבי יוחנן אסיפא פליג, Rabbi Yochanan a-seifa palig,
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's position is disagreeing with the second half
of the משנה, Mishna, which is about the milk. דרב
דאמר דברי הכל. De Rav d'amar divrei hakol. And רב Rav's position
applies to both
statements, that is רבנן Rabbanan and רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Ve-amar Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav.
Now we have another, now the fourth or really the third in
this sequence of statements of רב יהודה Rabbi Yehuda quoting רב. Rav.
ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Ve-amar Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav.
חבית מלאה מים שנפלה לים הגדול. A chavit meleia mayim she-nafla le-yam
ha-gadol. A barrel of water that fell into the ocean. Okay, so
what happened? The barrel is a you know large barrel that fell
into the ocean. What
happens? הטובל שם לא עלתה לו טבילה. Ha-tovel sham lo alta lo
tvila. A person who טובל tovels there, who immerses themselves to try
to be going to the מקווה mikveh there, there's a debate in
the ראשונים Rishonim what "there" means, we'll get to that...
where's the barrel, look... but one second...
does it mean where the water from the barrel spilled out into
or does it mean... oh I can draw a picture... or does
it mean
where in the barrel. So if we imagine...
why would you be טובל toveling in a barrel?
So here's our ocean, right? So and the barrel fell in, right?
So and then we assume there's some water exchange between the barrel
and the ocean, right? Perhaps. So possibility number one is there's some
there's some area in the ocean which now has barrel water in
it
and that would be therefore if you טובל tovel in this water
then it doesn't count because the water came from the barrel isn't
ocean water. That's possibility number one. Possibility number two is just to
say, oh, if you... if a barrel falls into the ocean and
the water stayed in the barrel, you can't טובל tovel in the
barrel.
But then wouldn't that be obvious if the water stayed in the
barrel? No, not
necessarily. Oh, you're saying that we're assuming that the water stayed in
the barrel, not that we know the water stayed in the barrel.
Right, but meaning the barrel is not totally watertight, so the assumption
would be that the water in the barrel in some way is
still connected to the ocean.
Why isn't it בטל *batel* somewhere else if a whole ocean?
Right, but the question. So anyway, but this becomes an interesting, it
becomes an important question in מקוה Mikvah *mikva* for thinking about for
thinking about someone who needs to טובל tovel *tovel* with a cast
in a plastic bag or something like that, or many different kinds
of questions relate to this issue, or questions of what constitutes מים
שאובים mayim she'uvim *mayim she'uvim*. It was water but then it fell,
the whole container fell into the ocean, is it diluted or not?
These kinds of questions. So what do we say? If you טובל
*tovel* there, whatever there means, לא עלתה לו טבילה *lo alta lo
tvila*, the טבילה *tvila* doesn't count, חיישינן לשלושה לוגין שלא יהא במקום
אחד *chaishinan lishlosha lugin shelo yihe b'makom echad*. We're concerned that perhaps
there are three לוג log *log* of מים שאובים mayim she'uvim. *mayim
she'uvim* within whatever 40 סאה *se'ah* you draw for the מקוה *mikva*,
right? The size of the מקוה *mikva* has to be 40 סאה
*se'ah*, right? And within that, if there are three לוג *log*
of מים שאובים *mayim she'uvim*, it's going to פסל *passel* the מקוה
*mikva*. So and again, does that mean before or after there were
40 סאה *se'ah*? But what this sort of means is you draw
an imaginary box around your מקוה *mikva* zone within the whole ocean
and then you say, oh, but there maybe there's three לוג *log*
of מים שאובים *mayim she'uvim* within my within my potential 40 סאה
*se'ah* מקוה *mikva*. So it's a sort of subdividing the whole ocean,
which is an interesting question, because normally I would think, oh, the
ocean is the ocean, this amount of water is totally inconsequential to
the entire ocean and therefore it doesn't matter, it should be just
totally בטל *batel* in the whole ocean. But we say no, we
actually see the water as localized. One of the more interesting interpretations
quoted by the ריטב"א *Ritva*, and and this is a rarity, is
the interpretation of רבי משה הדרשן *Rabbi Moshe HaDarshan*. I think the
ראב"ד Ra'avad *Ravad* quotes רבי משה הדרשן *Rabbi Moshe HaDarshan*. I think
people more familiar with רבי משה הדרשן *Rabbi Moshe HaDarshan* from when
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* quotes him על התורה *al haTorah*. He was a
דרשן *darshan*, he wasn't a תלמוד *Talmud* scholar necessarily. But he has
an interpretation of this סוגיא *sugya* that relates to this and he
talks actually about the different densities of fresh water and salt water,
that salt water is denser and so it prevents mixing. And that's
the issue, is that you have a barrel of fresh water that's
spilled over and poured into a specific area in the ocean, it
may not necessarily mix right away. Normally with a מקוה *mikva* we
say, oh, מים שאובים *mayim she'uvim* falls into the מקוה *mikva* or
whatever, it's because they're both fresh water, we assume they mix readily.
But because ocean water is of a different density, they may not
necessarily mix at the same rate. He had a very, you know,
scientific perspective to this סוגיא *sugya*, I think it's interesting, go see
it in the ריטב"א *Ritva*.
So, I mean, you just wait a little while, you can still
go there, just like five minutes, right? It'll be good, presumably.
I don't
know, it fell into the ocean, you חיישינן *chaishinan*, right? We say
חיישינן לשלושה לוגין שלא יהא במקום אחד *chaishinan lishlosha lugin shelo yihe
b'makom echad*. Okay, fine.
Go back tomorrow, I'm sure it'll be
fine, they won't say that. For sure, not tomorrow won't be a
problem. So how soon after? Enough time for the water to mix
and disperse and whatever. Okay, and we say ודווקא *v'davka*, sorry, ודווקא
לים הגדול
*v'davka l'yam hagadol*. We specifically say this about the ocean, דקאי וקיימא
*d'ka'i v'kaima*, because the water remains in place.
I don't know why you'd say that, there's always waves, there's underwater.
There are waves and whatever, but basically the same water is in
more or less the same area. אבל נהרא בעלמא *aval nahara b'alma*,
but in general applying to a river, no. What's interesting about this
also is a whole question of whether can you טובל *tovel* in
a מקוה *mikva* in a river, is a river a good מקוה
*mikva* or not? If the river is fed by spring water, then
it's like a מעיין *mayan*. And then it would be totally fine
to טובל *tovel* in flowing water. But rainwater has to be stationary
in order to be used as a מקוה *mikva*. And this comes
up in מסכת נידה *Masechet Niddah* and comes up in מסכת שבת
*Masechet Shabbat* and בכורות *Bechorot* and there's an extensive discussion in תוספות
*Tosafot* and ר"ן *Ran* in נדרים *Nedarim* about this, but anyway, okay.
About using a river as a מקוה *mikva*. Okay, אבל נהרא בעלמא
*aval nahara b'alma*, okay.
תניא נמי הכי *tanya nami hachi*. So if you're saying that if
it's a if it's a river that's fed
by spring water, then it's a מעיין
*mayan* and you can use it.
Right, but their assumption is a river that you would normally be
able to use as a מקוה *mikva*, if a barrel of water
falls into it, it's not a problem because the current is always
driving the water down so if you טובל *tovel* in the same
place where the barrel fell in, it won't be a problem.
Why does it why does it have to be stationary if it's
rainwater?
Because that's the הלכה halacha *halacha*, it's from the ספרא *Sifra*. It's
just a מקוה *mikva* is a מקוה *mikva* and a מעיין *mayan*
is a מעיין *mayan* and they're two different things and they operate
differently. Oh. So
but they're different. So the מדרש *midrash* is that oh, a מעיין
*mayan* is even זוחלין *zochalin*, even while it's flowing, and a מקוה
*mikva*, מקוה מים *mikve mayim*, בור *bor*, it has to be באשבורן
*be'ashboran*, it has to be stationary water. If it's from rainwater. If
it's from spring water, then it's a מעיין *mayan*, it doesn't matter.
So
you'd have to be in a stationary area in the river, right?
What do you mean?
I mean, the water can't be moving while you're while
you immerse in the if it were a river and the river
is constituted mainly by rainwater, which is usually true, then in order
to count as a מקוה *mikva* according to most opinions, the water
would have to be stationary. רבינו תם *Rabeinu Tam* goes through
a whole... Right, so that's just saying that this discussion here, oh,
a river, river, the point of the river is just to say
the water is flowing and therefore this is not a problem. The
question of whether you can טובל in the river for other reasons
is bracketed by this discussion. Okay. תני נמי הכי, Tani nami hachi,
we have a ברייתא Braita that supports this discussion as well. חבית
מלאה יין שנפל לים הגדול, Chavit mele'a yayin she'nafal l'yam hagadol, what
about a barrel of wine that fell into the ים הגדול? Yam
HaGadol? הטובל שם לא עלתה לו טבילה, Ha'tovel sham lo alta lo
tevilah, and if you טובל there it doesn't count. Again, the same
'there'. Is it in the barrel or just in the water near
the barrel? חיישינן לשלושה לוגים שאובים שלא יהיו במקום אחד. Chayshinan lishlosha
lugin she'uvim shelo yiheyu bemakom echad. We're worried that there are three
לוג of מים שאובים that are not in one place. But wait
a second, the problem of wine is not a problem of מים
שאובים. The problem of wine is that it's not water. So it's
actually a little bit of the text of the ברייתא Braita is
a little bit difficult anyway. Okay. And the ברייתא Braita continues, וכן
כיכר של תרומה שנפלה שם טמאה. Ve'chen kikar shel terumah shenafela sham
tamei. And if a loaf of תרומה terumah bread, of חלה Challah
bread fell into that area, טמא, tamei, it becomes טמא. tamei. Why?
Okay. So we see.
So מאי וכן? Mai ve'chen? Why? Why does the ברייתא Braita say
וכן, ve'chen, like it's a next step of the argument, an inference
or a further conclusion? מהו דתימא התם וכי גברא אחזקתיה? Mahu detema
hatam u'ki gavra achazkatei? Maybe I would say וכי גברא אחזקתיה, u'ki
gavra achazkatei, that is, someone who is טמא tamei טובלס tovels in
this spot in the ocean and he remains in the same status,
that is, was טמא, tamei, remains טמא. tamei. Maybe I should say
וכי תרומה אחזקתה, u'ki terumah achazkatah, that the תרומה terumah was טהור,
tahor, so it should remain טהור. tahor. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma
lan, it's even worse actually. It's we say וכי גברא אחזקתיה u'ki
gavra achazkatei that the מקוה doesn't have the power to remove the
טומאה, tumah, but also the problem of the of the wine is
that it's a משקים mashkim and the bread that touches it and
whatever, all these other issues, so that makes the bread טמא tamei
for this concern and that's an issue even so it's not even
just enough to say we should say
leave the תרומה terumah in its status quo position. Actually, we bump
it down a notch. We say that the תרומה terumah is טמא.
tamei. Okay. Next משנה, Mishna, back to עדים זוממים. Eidim zomemim. מעידים
אנו באיש פלוני שחייב לחברו מאתיים זוז. Me'idim anu be'ish ploni she'chayav
le'chavero matayim zuz. If the witnesses come and testify that so and
so owes his friend $200 ונמצאו זוממים ve'nimtze'u zomemim and they're proved
to have been conspiring, לוקין ומשלמים. lokin u'meshalmim. They receive lashes and
they pay. We're going to see, this is one of the core
מחלוקות machlokot in עדים זוממים. eidim zomemim. There are three three or
four points that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and and the חכמים Chachamim
disagree about, and this is the first of several.
Because you have והיה אם בן הכות הרשע. Ve'haya im bin hakot
harasha. The thing is that it always happens as well as ועשיתם
לו כאשר זמם
לעשות לאחיו.
Ve'asitem lo ka'asher zamam
la'asot l'achiv.
Right, so the principle of the ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו
Ve'asitem lo ka'asher zamam la'asot l'achiv principle would say, oh, they tried
to make him pay money so they have to pay money. And
they violated the איסור issur of being עדים זוממים eidim zomemim or
עדי שקר, edei sheker, therefore they're going to receive lashes. That and
it's going to be explained in the גמרא. Gemara. So let's just
see. Okay. שלא השם המביאן לידי מכות מביאן לידי תשלומין דברי רבי
מאיר. Shelo hashem hamevi'an lidei makot mevi'an lidei tashlumin divrei Rabbi Meir.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the same, the שם, shem, that is,
not the category of law, the same legal legal
ruling, the שם, shem, that is, which which rule did you break?
So you have to point to a specific rule. השם המביאן לידי
מכות, Hashem hamevi'an lidei makot, the one that makes them liable for
lashes is not the same violation as what makes them pay money.
So they're actually violating two different violations according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. וחכמים אומרים כל המשלם אינו לוקה. Ve'chachamim omrim kol hamishalem eino
lokeh.
The חכמים Chachamim disagree with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and say any
circumstance where a person will pay money they do not receive lashes.
You can't, it's sort of a double jeopardy principle that is for
the same crime you can't both pay and receive lashes. Okay. מעידים
אנו באיש פלוני שהוא חייב מלקות ארבעים. Me'idim anu be'ish ploni she'hu
chayav malkot arba'im. What if they testify that someone has violated a
certain עבירה aveira whose punishment is receiving lashes ונמצאו זוממים ve'nimtze'u zomemim
and they're shown to be conspiratorial, לוקים שמונים, lokim shmonim, משום לא
תענה ברעך עד שקר, mishum lo ta'aneh v'rei'acha ed shaker, because they
violated not testifying falsely against their friend ומשום ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם,
u'mishum ve'asitem lo ka'asher zamam, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says they receive eighty lashes because they violate two
different prohibitions. One because they testify falsely about a crime that you
would get lashes for and one because the general principle of כאשר
זמם. ka'asher zamam.
וחכמים אומרים אין לוקים אלא
ארבעים.
Ve'chachamim omrim ein lokim
ela arba'im.
And
the rabbis disagree with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and say you only
get forty lashes.
So forty lashes, thirty-nine or whatever, forty.
Well it would be thirty-nine or it would be seventy-eight, it would
be two two sets, right.
But you
can't you can't do
more than
than thirty-nine for a
single for the same sin.
But if you violate multiple, we're going to see in the third
פרק, perek, there'll be some very perhaps fanciful imaginations of how many
different violations can you violate with a single action? So you were
plowing in your field on יום טוב. Yom Tov. You're plowing on
יום טוב Yom Tov during שמיטה shmita
with... A donkey and an ox together, and you were plowing a
field that was כלאים, Kilayim, and all these other things. So maybe
you'll be five or six or seven or eight different violations, so
we compound. For each violation you'll get thirty-nine lashes. So actually you
could, it could...
didn't we have on bottom of yesterday? You taught it even? Yeah.
אמר עולא תדע שאילו עשו מעשה היו נהרגין ומשלמין. Amar Ulla teda
she-ilu asu maaseh hayu neharagin umeshalmin. Yeah,
what?
So we have that?
ונהרגין ומשלמין? venaharagin umeshalmin? Right. So that was only according to רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, who says you can do
לוקה ומשלם?
lokeh umeshalem? Where was
that?
Very bottom of
the back, ב עמוד
ב?
bet amud
bet?
How about the whole thing of רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Yeah, the
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva thing. ב עמוד ב. bet amud bet.
תדע
שאילו עשו מעשה
היו נהרגין ומשלמין.
teda she-ilu asu maaseh hayu neharagin
umeshalmin. Right, but that's about the קנס. knas. We're going to see.
The different קנס knas is different and we can see. Okay. בשלמא
לרבנן, Bishlama le-Rabbanan, I understand the position of רבנן, Rabbanan, that is
the חכמים Chachamim who disagree with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because כדי
רשעתו k'dei rishato כתיב, ktiv, משום רשעה אחת אתה מחייבו ואי אתה
מחייבו משום שתי רשעיות. mishum rishah achat atah mechayvo ve-i atah mechayvo
mishum shtei rishayot.
So that is כדי רשעתו. k'dei rishato. In the describing the giving
of lashes, you give him lashes כדי רשעתו k'dei rishato according to
his violation. That is only one violation have you violated a single
time, so then therefore you only get one set of lashes. That
is, the rabbis say for being עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, you're going
to get one set of מכות. makot. But according to רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, you're going to get two. You're going to get one
for עד שקר ed sheker and one for עד זומם. ed zomem.
And those
are... Noshi had some in there but she doesn't like it. Okay.
אלא לרבי מאיר מאי טעמא אמר עולא. Ella le-Rabbi Meir mai taama
amar Ulla.
So what about רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? What's his reasoning? אמר עולא.
Amar Ulla. עולא Ulla says גמר ממוציא שם רע. gamar mi-motzi shem
ra. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir derives it from מוציא שם רע. motzi
shem ra. The מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra is a case
where a husband falsely accuses his wife of having
been... she may need to eat which I can't feed her right
now.
She does, but I don't have it, it takes time. Okay. גמר
ממוציא שם רע. gamar mi-motzi shem ra. מה מוציא שם רע לוקה
ומשלם. mah motzi shem ra lokeh umeshalem. So a case of מוציא
שם רע, motzi shem ra, the husband accuses his wife of infidelity
during the אירוסין erusin period, and therefore, and there's a קנס knas
that goes along with it and the husband will get מכות makot
as well. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir derives from that, just like
מוציא שם רע לוקה ומשלם אף כל לוקה ומשלם. motzi shem ra
lokeh umeshalem af kol lokeh umeshalem. Every case of these kinds of
עדים זוממים edim zomemim cases, you'll both get lashes and you'll have
to pay.
Why is מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra like the paradigm? Because
it mentions it once and then mentions it once the...
very good. If you're trying to build a paradigm, you find a
paradigmatic case, you say it's a בנין אב binyan av and whatever
and there you go. Right. So and again, this is not רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir explicitly saying this, this is just עולא Ulla saying
this about רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay. I feel bad. Thank you.
Okay. מה מוציא שם רע שכן קנס. mah motzi shem ra she-ken
knas. But
the objection to עולא's Ulla suggestion is that is that by מוציא
שם רע, motzi shem ra, it's not a like I was saying
before, there's a difference between restitution and punitive payments. קנס Knas is
a punitive payment, it's a fine. So with מוציא שם רע, motzi
shem ra, the payment is a קנס. knas. סבר לה כרבי עקיבא
דאמר עדים זוממים קנסא הוא. savar lah k'Rabbi Akiva d'amar edim zomemim
knasa hu.
So mean then it's not representative?
It's well not just that it's not representative, it's that in the
first in the case the עדים זוממים edim zomemim we were talking
about the payment we thought that they were going to make was
was a restitution of the hypothetical loan or theft or whatever that
they were trying to accuse this person of of owing. So they
were trying to to impose a payment of ממון mamon of a
restitution payment. So therefore their payment would also be a restitution, it's
not a קנס. knas. But so the defense will be that רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir holds like רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position like we
saw yesterday that the entire institution of עדים זוממים edim zomemim and
the punishment involved is a קנס. knas. דאמר עדים זוממים קנסא הוא.
d'amar edim zomemim knasa hu. So and therefore, oh we've learned from
מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra to apply to עדים זוממים edim
zomemim as well, both of them are a case of קנס, knas,
so it would be consistent. Okay. איכא דמתני להא דעולא אהא דתניא.
Ika d'matni le-ha d'Ulla a-ha d'tanya. So there are those who explain
עולא's Ulla position like this or taught עולא's Ulla position this way
using this ברייתא. braita. לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר, Lo totiru mimenu
ad boker, using the principle of נותר. notar. Okay. והנותר ממנו עד
בוקר באש תשרוף. vehanotar mimenu ad boker ba-esh tisrof. So the prohibition
of נותר notar is if you have a קרבן korban that
certain קרבנות, korbanot, the meat of the קרבן korban is not allowed
to be left over until the morning after. Particularly true for קרבן
חטאת, korban chatat, קרבן פסח, korban pesach, a few other קרבנות korbanot
where the the initial קרבן אשם korban asham the eating is done
on the first day and the night afterward, but then by midnight
you have to finish and then if there's any left by morning
you have to burn it. So he says, the principle of נותר
notar is the classic example of the idea of לאו הניתק לעשה,
lav hanitak l'aseh, a prohibition. don't leave the meat over until morning,
but והנותר ממנו עד בוקר, ve-hanotar mimenu ad boker, if you do
leave it over until morning, then באש תשרוף, ba-esh tisoref, you have
to burn the meat. We learn from the principle of לאו הניתק
לעשה, lav hanitak la'aseh, a specific subcategory of prohibitions, that there's no
punishment that goes along with it because it has a corrective measure.
The הניתק לעשה, hanitak la'aseh, it's given over to a positive מצוה
mitzvah to correct the violation, so there's no punishment that goes along
with it because you just have an opportunity to fix it. And
it comes up in many different contexts, a whole discussion in פסחים
Pesachim about, about ביעור חמץ biur chametz perhaps related to that, about
how can you be violating בל יראה ובל ימצא bal yera’eh u-val
yimatzeh on פסח Pesach if you always have the opportunity to destroy
the חמץ chametz and maybe you won't be, you'll never violate the
prohibition. סמך ליה עשה אחר לא תעשה, samach lei assei achar lo
ta’asseh, the תורה Torah invokes a positive מצוה mitzvah after the prohibition,
לומר שאין לוקין עליו, lomar she-ein lokin alav, to tell you that
you did not get to get lashes for that, דברי רבי יהודה.
divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי עקיבא
אומר: Rabbi Akiva omer: לא מן השם הזה הוא זה, אלא משום
דהוי ליה לאו שאין בו מעשה. lo min hashem hazeh hu zeh,
ela mishum de-hava lei lav she-ein bo ma'aseh.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, the reason why you don't get
a punishment for נותר notar is not because of לאו הניתק לעשה,
lav hanitak la'aseh, it's because of לאו שאין בו מעשה. lav she-ein
bo ma'aseh. These are both subcategories of prohibitions. So לאו שאין בו
מעשה, lav she-ein bo ma'aseh, a prohibition that is not violated through
any active step. נותר והנותר ממנו עד בוקר באש תשרוף, notar ve-hanotar
mimenu ad boker ba-esh tisoref, if you left it over passively, then
you have violated the prohibition. But since I didn't do any action,
I just didn't eat it, by not eating it, it got left
over passively, so then there's no punishment because I didn't do anything.
You can't punish me for being inactive. So that's the principle of
לאו שאין בו מעשה. lav she-ein bo ma'aseh.
But, you know, it I guess depends how far you take that,
because like you say עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, I didn't do anything
but you testify...
Well, we're going to see, right here, right here, עדים זוממים edim
zomemim is suggested, at least by some, to be לאו שאין בו
מעשה.
lav she-ein
bo ma'aseh. We'll see. מכלל דרבי יהודה סבר לאו שאין בו מעשה
לוקין עליו? michlal de-Rabbi Yehuda savar lav she-ein bo ma'aseh lokin alav?
Does that mean that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks that actually, we
can infer from that, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks that for
a לאו שאין בו מעשה lav she-ein bo ma'aseh you would get
מכות? makot? That is even if it's a passive violation, you would
still be punished for it? So מנא ליה? mena lei? So where
does he learn that from? אמר עולא, amar Ulla, so where does
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda learn that you can get מכות makot for
לאו שאין בו מעשה? lav she-ein bo ma'aseh? אמר עולא גמר ממוציא
שם רע, amar Ulla gamar mi-motzi shem ra, he learns it from
מוציא שם רע. motzi shem ra. מה מוציא שם רע לאו שאין
בו מעשה? mah motzi shem ra lav she-ein bo ma’aseh? Just like
מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra is לאו שאין בו מעשה, lav
she-ein bo ma’aseh, the husband just gets up and accuses his wife,
but there's no physical action. You could say, wait a second, coming
to court and accusing your wife already is an action in some
way. So, and often in the questions of לאו שאין בו מעשה
lav she-ein bo ma'aseh you get into strange area of like, wait
a second, is that really not a מעשה? ma'aseh?
One of the famous examples I can think of now is רמב"ם
Rambam and the ראב"ד Ra'avad have a disagreement about לא תחמוד. lo
tachmod. לא תחמוד, lo tachmod,
the reason why you don't, you, there's no מכות makot for the
איסור issur of לא תחמוד. lo tachmod. לא תחמוד lo tachmod from
the Ten Commandments is pressuring someone until they sell you something. So
it's not stealing it, but it's exerting enough pressure that someone is
compelled to sell you something they didn't want to sell you. Coercion.
Coercion. So the רמב"ם Rambam says, oh, the reason why you don't
get מכות makot is because לאו שאין בו מעשה. lav she-ein bo
ma'aseh. But
then in the previous הלכה halacha he says, oh, but you're only
violate it once you pressure him so much that he's able to,
that he's finally convinced to sell. So you say, wait a second,
there is an action, you have to be pressuring the person. And
the ראב"ד disagrees, he says the reason why you don't get מכות
makot is because לאו הניתן לתשלומין, lav hanitan letashlumin, it's something that's
given to be paid back, like גניבה gneivah and גזילה gezeilah and
things like that. That's why, that's why you don't get מכות makot
for it. So it's an interesting discussion of what constitutes an אין
בו מעשה. ein bo ma'aseh.
Okay, but they say if I'm, if I'm עדים זוממים edim zomemim
and I say you've stole, it's also ניתן לתשלומין, nitan letashlumin, but
yet according to that first opinion you do get מכות. makot.
Right, so again, according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it wouldn't get
you out of it. So that's an interesting point as well. Because
he says, oh, it's just like מוציא שם רע, motzi shem ra,
מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra there's a קנס knas and there's
a מכות, makot, right?
Is the coercion has to be a physical
coercion or can be psychological?
No, it could be psychological. You just always badgering the person, hey,
I really like your watch, I really like your watch, I really
like your watch, every single day,
that has to be an act, if you consider it an act.
But that's an interesting point there of like is that really an
action or not? רמב"ם Rambam thinks no, רמב"ם Rambam thinks that's אין
בו מעשה, ein bo ma'aseh, it's not an active step.
It would require the physical act.
Right, the physical act is like taking it in some way, right?
A verbal, a speech act is not the same. It's very interesting
for this discussion. Okay, אף כל לאו שאין בו מעשה לוקין עליו.
af kol lav she-ein bo ma'aseh lokin alav. So maybe we should
say every, so for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we can derive that
every לאו שאין בו מעשה lav she-ein bo ma'aseh you, you would
get lashes. מה למוציא שם רע שכן לוקה ומשלם? mah le-motzi shem
ra she-ken lokeh u-meshalem? So מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra you
get lashes and you pay, and therefore we can, so we could
derive from מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra that that would be
the general principle. אלא אמר ריש לקיש, ela amar Reish Lakish, ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish says, גמר מעדים זוממים, gamar me-edim zomemim, that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda learns it from עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. מה עדים
זוממים לאו שאין בו מעשה? mah edim zomemim lav she-ein bo ma'aseh?
Just like עדים זוממים edim zomemim is a לאו שאין בו מעשה,
lav she-ein bo ma'aseh, has no action, because all you do is
show up in court and testify, but you didn't do any action
to the person in any physical way, it's just a speech
act. לוקין עליו, lokin alav, and you would get lashes nonetheless. אף
כל לאו שאין בו מעשה לוקין עליו. af kol lav she-ein bo
ma'aseh lokin alav. That's where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda derives it from.
He derives it from עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. מה לעדים זוממים שכן
אין צריכין התראה? mah le-edim zomemim she-ken ein tzrichin hatra'ah? But there's
a special rule, עדים זוממים edim zomemim is one of the few...
עבירות aveirot that don't need warning. We heard about this already in
מסכת סנהדרין Masechet Sanhedrin that some of the more either more core
עבירות aveirot in some way they're meant to be more obvious or
we need to root them out without the delay of having to
rely on התראה hatra'ah or not. So עדים זוממים edim zomemim because
a basic principle of the legal system, you can't conspire to testify
falsely against people, so therefore we would assume that or the הלכה
is that we don't we don't require you the witnesses the because
again it would also be impossible, right? Think about it. If the
whole point is that this is a conspiracy and the proof against
it is או עמנו הייתם, o imanu heyitem, you only find out
that the עמנו הייתם imanu heyitem was relevant
afterwards, two weeks later when they go to to testify in court.
So there is no potential for התראה hatra'ah either. There's no there
would be no way for us to punish them if we would
rely on התראה hatra'ah because there's no
circumstance where it would make sense. So that's also part of the
calculation here.
So so in effect there's a quasi התראה hatra'ah because you tell
them understand that you're witnesses, you're supposed to be telling the truth.
Right, but that's the part of the court proceedings already. It's not
at the time that they violate the prohibition, right? They earned their
well it's an interesting question. Do they earn their do they earn
their מכות makot in court or do they earn it when they
come up with the conspiracy two weeks ago? Right, that's also the
question, which
which again maybe like you're saying, oh, they only earn it in
court so maybe the דרישה וחקירה derisha v'chakirah in court counts as
a התראה hatra'ah of some sort. So but do they have to
explicitly say 'If you are עדים זוממים edim zomemim you have you
will be punished with reciprocal punishment' and they'll say 'Yes, I understand
and על מנת כן' al menat ken and all these other things
like you know. So okay, מוציא שם רע יוכיח. motzi shem ra
yochiach. So now so because we have two different conflicting sources. On
the one hand we have the source, oh maybe you can derive
it from מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra and maybe you can
derive it from עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. So מוציא שם רע יוכיח,
motzi shem ra yochiach, so you can learn from מוציא שם רע.
motzi shem ra. וחזר הדין v'chazar hadin so that is if both
of these, this is often where you see with Talmudic סוגיות sugyot
that discuss 'Oh, we're deriving a principle from a certain source' and
it says 'But wait a second, each of them there are two
potential sources. If you have two sources, now we don't have a
good proof because two sources means they were exceptional cases, not that
they're meant to be a general principle derived from this case.' So
וחזר הדין ולא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה.
v'chazar hadin v'lo rei zeh k'rei zeh v'lo rei zeh k'rei
zeh. They each have differences, that is they're not comparable one to
the other. הצד השוה שבהן, hatzad hashavah shebehen, what's what's the constant
between the two
cases? לאו שאין בו מעשה lav she-ein bo ma'aseh ולוקין עליו, v'lokin
alav, and you get lashes for them. אף כל לאו שאין בו
מעשה לוקין עליו. af kol lav she-ein bo ma'aseh lokin alav. So
that would be the proof for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that לאו
שאין בו מעשה lav she-ein bo ma'aseh you still get מלקות. malkot.
Why they might say that it's that the reason you don't get
מלקות malkot for אונס ones is because it's לאו הניתק לעשה. lav
hanitak l'aseh. אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, whatever. Right, אלא מעתה.
ela me'ata.
But
it's לאו הניתק לעשה, lav hanitak l'aseh, right.
Because the whole thing about לאו
שאין בו מעשה.
lav she-ein
bo ma'aseh.
Exactly, right. Because according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda לאו שאין בו
מעשה lav she-ein bo ma'aseh you do get מלקות. malkot. You're setting
up an interference. Exactly, the way it's set up here, right. So
מה לצד השוה שבהן שכן קנס. mah l'tzad hashavah shebehen sheken knas.
But wait a second, there's also a commonality between the two of
them that they're both a קנס, knas, that is they're both some
prescribed fixed punishment in some way.
Now עדים זוממים edim zomemim that was debatable.
It's debatable, right. We saw the debate yesterday between רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that maybe it's not maybe it's not necessarily always understood clearly.
Right, it's only a
קנס, knas, why it's not... Okay. הא לא קשיא, ha lo kashya,
this is not a problem for him, רבי יהודה לא סבר לה
כרבי עקיבא. Rabbi Yehuda lo savar lah k'Rabbi Akiva. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda disagrees with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva about קנס. knas. אלא מה
לצד השוה שבהן שיש להן צד חמור. ela mah l'tzad hashavah shebehen
sheyesh lahen tzad chamur. But they are these are cases that are
more strict than other kinds of cases, that is מוציא שם רע
motzi shem ra and עדים זוממים edim zomemim are both very severe
violations. רבי יהודה צד חמור לא פריך. Rabbi Yehuda tzad chamur lo
parich.
But somehow how do we know if it's more severe, of course
we can't do that, like you know.
For certain things we can.
Does רש"י Rashi say what's more severe or something?
One second.
Because the חומרות chumrot of meaning on the one hand you could
say in general the sense that we have from them is, well
it's a לאו שאין בו מעשה lav she-ein bo ma'aseh or it's
a it's a I mean or it's לוקה ומשלם, lokeh umishalem, right?
the case of מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra or for עדים
זוממים edim zomemim also the argument would be that according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is לוקה ומשלם. lokeh umishalem. So that's the צד
חמור. tzad chamur.
But but this is all according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, how
do we know that he holds it's so חמור? chamur?
Well he doesn't. He says רבי יהודה צד חמור לא
פריך.
Rabbi Yehuda
tzad chamur
lo
parich.
Because they're each different. רש"י says לא פריך, lo parich, that is
הואיל וחומרו של זה אינו חומרו של זה אין טעם המלקות תלוי
בו. ho'il v'chumro shel zeh eino chumro shel zeh ein ta'am hamalkut
talui bo. It's not because it's more severe, it's just they each
have they each have their own ways in which they're more severe,
they each have their own ways in which they're more less severe,
so it's not not a defining characteristic.
So for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda they're not seen as exceptional cases,
they're seen as generative
example cases and therefore that's why רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda derives his
principle that he says לאו שאין בו מעשה lav she-ein bo ma'aseh
you do get מלקות, malkot, and for these cases according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir
possibly sort of set aside within רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position it's
possible to understand רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that you would say that
לוקה ומשלם. lokeh umishalem. והרבנן? V'ha-rabbanan?
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says לאו שאין בו מעשה lav she-ein bo
ma'aseh you are לוקין. lokin. Did you just say you're not?
Yeah רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, sorry, I said it wrong. לאו שאין
בו מעשה lav she'ein bo ma'aseh רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says you
do get, you do get מכות, makot, right? And the רבנן rabbanan
disagree with him. ורבנן, verabbanan, האי לא תענה ברעך עד שקר מאי
דרשי ביה? hai lo ta'aneh vere'acha ed shaker mai darshi bei?
So what do the Rabbis against רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, how do
they interpret the פסוק pasuk לא תענה ברעך עד שקר? lo ta'aneh
vere'acha ed shaker? Because in our משנה, mishnah, right, the proof for
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was that you violated the prohibition of testifying
falsely and you violated the prohibition of עדים זוממים. eidim zomemim. So
how could you violate both? Why do the Rabbis think you only
get one, one set of lashes? Okay, so what do they, how
do they interpret it? ההוא מיבעי ליה לאזהרה לעדים זוממים. hahu mibayei
lei le'azharah le'eidim zomemim. They use that פסוק pasuk not as a
proof for punishment as a separate violation, they use it as the
אזהרה, azharah, the warning for עדים זוממים. eidim zomemim. Interesting about that
is usually we only have the principle that you need both
an
אזהרה azharah and
an עונש onesh mentioned separately in the תורה Torah for capital crimes.
But since עדים זוממים eidim zomemim are at least potentially or sometimes
are for a capital crime, so that's why you would need two
mentions. So that's what the רבנן rabbanan interpret as. רבי מאיר, Rebbi
Meir, אזהרה לעדים זוממים מנא ליה? azharah le'eidim zomemim minalei? So how
does רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir derive that you need the אזהרה azharah
for that then? אמר רבי ירמיה, amar Rebbi Yirmeyah, נפקא ליה nafka
lei מן והנשארים ישמעו ויראו ולא יוסיפו עוד. min vahanish'arim yishme'u veyira'u
velo yosifu od.
So according to רבי ירמיה, Rebbi Yirmeyah, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir derives
the אזהרה azharah not from the principle of עד שקר ed shaker
but from the principle that other people will hear about it, one
of the four prohibitions that it requires הכרזה hachrazah to be announced
to the different communities. ורבנן, verabbanan, and how do
you get עדים זוממים eidim zomemim from that?
That's in the context of עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim, והנשארים ישמעו ויראו
ולא יוסיפו
עוד.
vahanish'arim yishme'u veyira'u velo
yosifu od. So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says that applies to, that's
the אזהרה azharah against עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim, other people shouldn't be
conspiring witnesses. ורבנן ההוא מיבעי ליה להכרזה. verabbanan hahu mibayelei lehachrazah. And
the Rabbis use that to require הכרזה. hachrazah. ורבי מאיר הכרזה מישמעו
ויראו נפקא. ve'Rebbi Meir hachrazah m'yishme'u veyira'u nafka. So רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir just derives that from the second part of the פסוק, pasuk,
the first part והנשארים vahanish'arim or ולא יוסיפו עוד, velo yosifu od,
you shouldn't continue doing this, that's the אזהרה, azharah, and then ישמעו
ויראו yishme'u veyira'u is the הכרזה. hachrazah. So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
can derive both principles from that פסוק. pasuk. רבנן rabbanan derive one
from one and one from the other, and that's why רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir can use the idea of עד שקר ed shaker to
say that there's a second violation. There are two violations for being
an עד זומם, ed zomem, one is just generally testifying falsely, and
the second is participating in a conspiracy to falsely accuse or falsely
convict someone. So those are two different violations according to רבי מאיר.
Rebbi Meir. According to רבנן, rabbanan, those are basically the same violation,
they're testifying falsely for the purposes of doing something negative to someone
else. Okay.
Okay, so
and the whole thing with, we had before, just so I can
understand this, the רבה Rabba thing, you know, so עצמתה atzamta and
נהרגים ומשלמים? neheragim u'meshalmim? Yeah, so
that's according to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, and then רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva or רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir be in the same camp where
you can get like two things?
I'm not sure that רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva would agree with this
רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, I think the point of רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva is sort of more within a kind of קים ליה בדרבה
מיניה kam lei biderabba minei kind of circumstance, whether we say that
the monetary violation and the capital or corporal punishment is in the
same category or not. So I think for רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva,
that's what's going on on דף ב. daf bet. Let's just do
the next משנה mishnah and the next little bit of גמרא gemara
before we finish up for today. משלשין בממון ואין משלשין במלקות. mishalshilin
bemamon ve'ein mishalshilin bemalkot. When there's a monetary claim against the עדים
זוממים, eidim zomemim, it gets subdivided between the witnesses. So if there
were four witnesses who participated in this conspiracy and they all testify,
"Oh, so-and-so owes a thousand dollars," so then the thousand dollars will
be split between the four of them and they each only pay
two hundred and fifty. Okay. ואין משלשין במלקות. ve'ein mishalshilin bemalkot. But
if four people testified that someone wore שעטנז shatnez and it turned
out that they were conspiring against him, he didn't wear שעטנז, shatnez,
so then each of them will get thirty-nine lashes. We don't subdivide
the lashes between the four witnesses. כיצד? keitzad? העידו שהוא חייב לחברו
מאתים זוז והוזמו, he'idu shehu chayav lechavero matayim zuz vehuzmumu, if they
testified that you owe two hundred dollars and they're shown to be
conspirators, משלשין ביניהם, mishalshilin beineihem, they divide the two hundred זוז zuz
between them. אבל אם העידו שהוא חייב מלקות ארבעים והוזמו, aval im
he'idu shehu chayav malkot arba'im vehuzmumu, if they've testified that he violated
some עבירה averah that he could get forty lashes for, כל אחד
ואחד לוקה ארבעים, kol echad ve'echad lokeh arba'im, then each one of
the witnesses will get forty lashes. מנא הני מילי? mina hanei milei?
The גמרא gemara asks where's this derived from? אמר אביי, amar Abaye,
נאמר רשע בחייבי מלקות, ne'emar rasha bechayavei malkot, it says that someone
is a רשע rasha regarding receiving lashes, ונאמר רשע בחייבי מיתות, vene'emar
rasha bechayavei mitot, and it says that you're רשע rasha for capital
crimes. Okay. מיתת בית דין. mita beis din.
By capital crimes. מה להלן אין מיתה לחצי, mah lehalan ein mita
lachatzi, just like there's no half death, you can't half-kill someone, okay,
אף כאן אין מלקות לחצי, af kan ein malkot lachatzi,
there's also no such thing as half מכות. makot. Okay, so point
is that מכות makot are always meted out in groups of thirty-nine.
That's The minimum and the maximum per chunk. And obviously for multiple
violations you could receive multiple sets of lashes, but the sense is
that any individual crime cannot receive partial lashes. Okay.
Is that a logical parallel to half death? It's obvious, he's dead.
But half מלקות malkut you could get half מלקות.
malkut. Right. So it's a very interesting question and it gets much
discussed, it's like, well, is this really not possible or not? I'll
try to bring some more additional sources about that from tomorrow.
Well it
sort of is a proxy
for מיתה mitah then?
Well it sort of is. And this is much discussed, right? So
the idea is in many ways מלקות malkut are seen not as
a separate category from מיתה mitah but actually as a sub-category. There
are actually five or six different kinds of מיתה, mitah, right? There's
סקילה שריפה הרג חנק. sekilah srefah hereg chenek. There's
כיפה, kipah, which is something different. There's you don't get עולם הבא,
olam haba, we had a whole פרק perek about that. And there's
מלקות. malkut. And מלקות malkut you don't die from it but it's
almost like you were supposed to die but let's like we're not
going to kill you all the way. We're going to give you
מלקות malkut instead. And מלקות malkut we give a specific fixed amount.
And you find an atonement מלקות malkut also?
Well you saw that in the beginning, the whole question of whether
it's כפרה kapparah or not and all these kind of things. גוף
לכפרה, guf lekapparah, so מלקות malkut we're going to see. I mean
it generally the sense is that any of the punishment that בית
דין beit din gives is meant to be a כפרה kapparah in
some way. It's going to be both. It's a punishment and it's
an atonement and
it's, yeah exactly, it's a deterrent.
It's a deterrent, right, there are many different and these are a
whole, you know there's a whole philosophy of
criminal law and you know all the different goals. You know now
we think about a criminal justice system, what are the different goals?
So we also have in our society now a sense of, oh,
punishment should be rehabilitation as well. You should take someone who's a
criminal and help them reform themselves in some way. But the halakhic
system doesn't see rehabilitation as the task of the court. That's a
task, individual responsibility. Rehabilitation, that's a whole process of תשובה, teshuvah, but
that's a separate separate sense, but they're all different pieces of that.
Okay. So, okay, אף כאן אין מלקות לחציה. af kan ein malkut
lachatzyah. רבא אמר, Rava amar, so רבא Rava disagrees with אביי. Abaye.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, בעינן כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו וליכא. ba'inan ka'asher
zamam la'asot le'achiv velo ika. So רבא Rava says you have to
do according to what they wanted to do to their friend. If
you try to give them only ten מלקות malkut each, that's not
what they were trying to do, they were trying to give him
thirty-nine lashes. So it has to be, it's intrinsic to the nature
of עדים זוממים edim zomemim that it has to be something which
was what they were potentially trying to do. They split the money
then. Okay. אי הכי ממון נמי. i hachi mamon nami. There you
go, then you should say the money each one of them should
have to pay the full amount of the money. We say no,
ממון מצטרף. mamon mitztaref.
Money joins together. If you have two hundred fifty dollars, two hundred
fifty dollars, two hundred fifty dollars, two hundred fifty dollars, that's a
thousand dollars. But מלקות לא מצטרף. malkut lo mitztaref. The point is
that the punishment, the physical corporal punishment that each person receives, we
can't group together their subjective human experience and say that they're all
part of the same the same group and tell me, oh, they
wanted to give thirty-nine lashes so each one of them will get
ten. Well no, the suffering and the pain and the whatever it
is that this person will get out of thirty-nine lashes is not
the same as what four people will get from having ten lashes
each. It's a different, qualitatively different experience. And therefore that, that's the
point that's being made there.
And also if they each gave the total amount of money then
the person who received much more than he's entitled to.
Right, but we see that as well. Again, this person didn't have
to pay anything, right? They're not paying back anything that was stolen.
They're all paying back what was potentially to have been stolen. So
there's his net win, right? You want to get rich, get other
people to conspire against you and make sure that they get convicted,
right? Then you, right? But no, it's a strange kind of a
thing which is a, like, oh, they testify about, oh, you know
David you owe so-and-so a lot of money and then it turns
out no no no you already paid him back so now you
get a nice, you know, חנוכה Chanukkah bonus on there, right? So
okay, everybody have a great day, we'll pick up, we'll pick up
on ה עמוד ב he amud bet tomorrow and sorry about earlier
about the interruptions. תודה רבה. toda raba.